A Guide to the Papers of the Conservation Council of Virginia, 1969-1987
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Conservation Council of Virginia, 1969-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9883-e
This collection contains 1,675 items (9 Hollinger boxes, ca. 3.5 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records were given to the Library by Mrs. Nancy Summer, Richmond, Virginia, on April 2, 1992.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Conservation Council of Virginia was formed in 1969 as a decentralized coalition of approximately forty Virginia environmental groups whose main purpose was to act as an organizing agency for the participating groups in lobbying for common state environmental goals. The collection also contains the records of the Conservation Council of Virginia Foundation (incorporated in 1975) a non-profit, tax exempt organization created by the members of the C.C.Va. "to promote the education of the public on environmental matters in Virginia in order to foster informed environmental decisions and responsible citizen participation on the decision making process." It replaced - on the state level - the Central Atlantic Environment Center, which had provided information and staff services to the C.C. Va. since its inception. The Foundation published The Virginia Environmental Legislation Reporter and a bimonthly newsletter and conducted workshops, conferences, and seminars on environmental problems, to help carry out its educational function. In 1981, the Conservation Council of Virginia and the Conservation Council of Virginia Foundation merged and the surviving organization was known as the Conservation Council of Virginia Foundation.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of the Conservation Council of Virginia (abbreviated as C.C.Va.) contains ca. 1,675 items (9 Hollinger boxes, ca. 3.5 linear feet), 1969-1987, consisting of three types of records: 1) organizational records, which include minutes, correspondence, incorporation papers, resolutions, financial statements, long-range planning records, legislative priorities & lobbying, membership lists, tax records, newsclippings & press coverage, reports, and recommendations; 2) committee records; and 3) topical files concerning environmental issues and the positions of the C.C.Va., projects, resolutions, specific legislation, conferences, forums, and workshops, including eight cassette tape recordings of C.C.Va. conferences and forums.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Series I: Organizational Records (Boxes 1-4)
Series II: Council Committees (Box 5)
Series III: Topical Files (Boxes 5-9)
Cassette Tapes T-941 - T-948
Arrangement
The collection is organized alphabetically by file name within each of three series and chronologically within each folder.
Contents List
- Organizational Records
  - Bound Volume of C.C. Va. Minutes, Resolutions, etc. 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Bound Volume of C.C.Va. Minutes, Resolutions, etc. 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Bound Volume of C.C.Va. Minutes, Resolutions, etc. 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Corporate Records of the Conservation Council of Virginia Foundation 1975-1979, 1 Volume (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1979-1985 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with Senators Byrd, Warner, and Trible 1981-1983 (Box 2)
  - Financial Statements of the Conservation Council of Virginia Foundation 1976-1984 & 1987 (Box 2 folders)
  - Five Year Work Plan Conservation Council of Virginia Foundation 1982 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Priorities of the C.C.Va. 1973-1987 (Box 3)
  - List of C.C.Va. Resolutions 1969-1974 (Box 3)
  - Lists of C.C.Va. Board of Directors & Organizational Members 1974-1978, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Minutes of the Meetings of the C.C.Va. 1972-1979, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Minutes of the Meetings of the C.C.Va. Foundation 1977-1980 (Box 3)
  - Minutes of the Annual Meetings of the C.C.Va. 1973-1979, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Minutes of the Joint Board Meetings of the C.C.Va. & the C.C.Va. Foundation 1977-1980, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Press Coverage 1972-1979 (Box 4)
  - Registration Fee & Franchise Tax of the C.C.Va. Foundation 1979-1983 (Box 4)
  - Reports and Recommendations - Conservation Council of Virginia Foundation 1974-1979 (Box 4)
  - Tax Returns (Federal) of the C.C.Va. 1970-1976 (Box 4)
  - Tax Returns (State) of the C.C.Va. 1980-1981 (Box 4)
- Council Committees
  - Air Subcommittee 1982 (Box 5)
  - Energy Subcommittee 1982 (Box 5)
  - Hazardous Wastes Subcommittee 1982 (Box 5)
  - Issues Committee 1979-1982 (Box 5)
  - Land Use Subcommittee 1982 (Box 5)
  - Membership Committee 1981-1983 (Box 5)
  - Newsletter Committee 1982, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Nominating Committee 1981-1982 (Box 5)
  - Population Subcommittee 1982 (Box 5)
  - Solid Wastes Subcommittee 1982 (Box 5)
  - Water Subcommittee n.d. (Box 5)
  - Wetlands Subcommittee n.d. (Box 5)
- Topical Files
  - Acid Rain 1980-1984 (Box 5)
  - Agricultural Lands n.d. (Box 5)
  - Air Pollution Control, Air Quality & the Clean Air Act 1971-1977 (Box 5)
  - Alaskan Lands Conservation Act 1978 (Box 5)
  - Alaskan Pipeline 1973 (Box 5)
  - Assateague Island 1971-1975 (Box 5)
  - Auto Emission Control Devices Anti-Tampering Conference 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - Back Bay National Wildlife Refuge 1971-1978 (Box 5)
  - Back Bay-False Cape Task Force 1979-1983, n.d., 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Back Bay-False Cape Land Exchange Environmental Impact Statement 1983, 2 folders (Box 6)
    Draft & Final Report
  - Beach Front Protection Ordinance, Virginia Beach - Natural Resources Defense Council, Inc. 1978 Oct (Box 6)
  - Beverage Containers 1971-1978 (Box 6)
  - Blackwater Project 1974 (Box 6)
  - Bull Run Mountain 1973 (Box 6)
  - Capitol Expansion 1973-1974 (Box 6)
  - Coal Surface Mining 1970-1977 (Box 6)
  - Coastal Primary Sand Dune Protection Act 1987 (Box 6)
  - Commission of Outdoor Recreation Bond Issue 1969-1975 (Box 6)
  - Coors Brewery Adjacent to Shenandoah National Park 1980-1984 (Box 6)
  - Council on the Environment 1974-1979 (Box 6)
    Newsclippings & Statements from the C.C.Va.
  - Critical Environmental Areas 1973-1974 (Box 6)
  - Dams 1969-1975 (Box 6)
  - Dano Project, King George County 1979 (Box 6)
  - Delmarva Waterway 1972-1977 (Box 6)
  - Energy Crisis 1972-1977 (Box 6)
  - Environmental Activist Workshop 1982-1983 (Box 6)
  - Environmental Education 1972 (Box 6)
  - Environmental Impact Statements on State Highways 1977 (Box 6)
  - Environmental Management 1973-1975 (Box 6)
  - False Cape State Park 1971-1978 (Box 6)
  - False Cape State Park Task Force Reference Materials 1982 Jul, 1 volume (Box 7)
  - Fort Story Resolution 1974 (Box 7)
  - Gathright Dam 1973-1978 (Box 7)
  - Green Springs Region, Louisa County 1970-1977 (Box 7)
  - Growth Policies 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Historic Landmarks Commission Resolution 1978 (Box 7)
  - I-95 Circumferential Highway Around Richmond Resolution 1976-1979 (Box 7)
  - James River Basin Planning Advisory Committee Recommendation and Comments by the C.C.Va. re the Corps of Engineers Report 1973 & 1975 (Box 7)
  - Land Use Positions 1971-1975 (Box 7)
  - Manassas Battlefield Park 1977 (Box 7)
  - Mason Neck Closure n.d. (Box 7)
  - Ocean Dumping 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - Offshore Oil Drilling 1975 (Box 7)
  - Oil Spills Prevention Proposals & Testimony of Russell Scott 1978 (Box 7)
  - National Forest Planning Conference 1987 (Box 7)
  - Parham/Chippenham Connector & the Citizens Technical Advisory Committee 1984 (Box 7)
  - Phosphate Detergent Ban Resolution 1986 (Box 7)
  - Population Control & Family Planning 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Recycling in Virginia Conference 1987 (Box 7)
  - Richmond Flood Protection 1973 (Box 7)
  - Run-Off Workshop 1979-1980 (Box 7)
  - Scenic Highway Designation (Route 5) 1974-1977 (Box 7)
  - Scenic River Resolutions 1971-1978 (Box 7)
  - Seashore State Park 1978 (Box 7)
  - Sewage Effluent and Sludge - Land Applications 1976 (Box 7)
  - Stream Channelization & Dredging 1973-1974 (Box 8)
  - Swann Oil Company Proposed Oil Refinery on Elizabeth River, Chesapeake Resolution 1979 (Box 8)
  - Timber Management 1976 (Box 8)
  - Toxic Substances Conferences 1978 Mar (Box 8)
  - Transportation, Dept. of 1973 (Box 8)
    Bill to Create
  - Virginia Constitutional Amendment 1970 (Box 8)
    Conservation (Article XI)
  - Virginia Environmental Legislation Reporter 1977-1980, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Virginia General Assembly 1980-1984, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Virginia General Assembly n.d. (Box 8)
    Legislative Information
  - Virginia General Assembly 1979-1984 (Box 8)
    Lobbying Records
  - Virginia General Assembly 1980 (Box 8)
    Roll Call Votes
  - Virginia General Assembly 1980 (Box 8)
    Volunteer Thank You Letter
  - Virginia Outdoor Foundation 1978 (Box 9)
    Reorganization
  - Virginia Rivers and Waters Conference 1979 (Box 9)
  - Virginia Waste Exchange 1982 (Box 9)
  - Virginia Water Control Board Issues 1971-1977 (Box 9)
  - Waste Alert Grant 1980-1982, 2 folders (Box 9)
    Expenses
  - Waste Alert Handbook and Conference 1981-1982 (Box 9)
  - Water Pollution Control Act 1974-1977 (Box 9)
  - Water Resource Management 1969-1978 (Box 9)
  - Water Study 1976-1979 (Box 9)
  - Wetlands Manual & Resolution n.d. (Box 9)
  - Wilderness Designations for Shenandoah National Park 1971-1978 (Box 9)
- C.C.Va. Conferences & Forums
  - "How to organize your group to lobby on ecological issues" (part 1) ca. 1980 (Box 9)
    A forum sponsored by the Conservation Council of Virginia, John Marlin, moderator. Participants include: Bob Bush (VA Canal & Navigation Society), Westvaco & Forestry Assn. Doug Turner (Patrick Henry Assn), Junius Fishburn (LJRA), Mike Turney (Brumley Gap Citizens), Tim Hartman (EPA liason), Jubina Smith (VA Farm Bureau).
  - "How to organize your group to lobby on ecological issues" (part 2) ca. 1980 (Box 9)
    A forum sponsored by the Conservation Council of Virginia, John Marlin, moderator. Topics include: "Fighting the U.S. Corps of Engineers"; "Effective Lobbying"; "Experience in Illinois"; "Environmental Action and Strategy".
  - "How to organize your group to lobby on ecological issues" (part 3) ca. 1980 (Box 9)
    A forum sponsored by the Conservation Council of Virginia, Peter K. Pettus, moderator. Panelists include: John Marlin (Illinois Environmental Council), Brent Blackwelder, Tom Evans, Pat McSweeney, Ernie Dickerman, (conclusion of conference).
  - "Weekend conference on organizing and legislation" ca. 1980 (Box 9)
    Sponsored by the Conservation Council of Virginia. Side A panelists include: Ed Clark (Staunton Scenic River / Dam Assn), Kirk Clarkson (C.A.R.E.), Julie Burke (Richmond), Memory Porter, and Tom Evans. Side B panelists include: Tom Evans, Memory Porter, Doug Wynett (Washington,D.C.).
  - "CCVA Conference" 1980/1981 (Box 9)
    Sponsored by the Conservation Council of Virginia, Peter K. Pettus, moderator. Side A: "Gen. Brutethwackem" (comic re: Army Corps of Engineers), Organizations - activity reports: "Va. Bass - Sierra, etc." Side B participants include: Trout Unlimited Inc., York River Assn., Virginia Trails Assn., Float Fishermen Assn, and C.A.R.E. (CBF).
  - "Legislators talk with CCVA" (part 1) 1980 May 10 (Box 9)
    A conference sponsored by the Conservation Council of Virginia re: "successful lobbying," Peter K. Pettus, moderator. Side A: Edie Harrison (freshman Virginia delegate), Rick Boucher (Virginia delegate), and Frank Hall (Virginia delegate). Side B is blank.
  - "Legislators talk with CCVA" (part 2) 1980 May 10 (Box 9)
    A conference sponsored by the Conservation Council of Virginia re: "successful lobbying," Peter K. Pettus, moderator. Side A: "Lobbying - what is effective?" (continued on side B). Side B: JLARC (Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission) - "what it is, what is does".
  - "Legislators talk with CCVA" (part 3) 1980 May 10 (Box 9)
    A conference sponsored by the Conservation Council of Virginia re: "successful lobbying," Peter K. Pettus, moderator. Side A: JLARC session (continued from T-947). "Farmers in Va. - problems, land use and preservation"; Side B: "Farmers in Va." - continued "General discussion re: CCVA programs and goals." (conclusion of conference).